Finding Aid for Michael P. Church papers, 1933-1975
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michael P. Church papers 1933-1975
Church, Michael P., 1907-
85509 Aa 2
Director of cultural activities of the Extension Service of the University of Michigan. Material relating to the National Youth Administration and the effect of the depression on Michigan youth; files collected relating to Michigan cultural organizations, art festivals and exhibitions; notebooks containing biographical information on Michigan artists; and photographs.
10 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michael Church (donor no. 2313 ) began depositing materials with the library in 1947. He made numerous yearly deposits until his death.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Michael P. Church was with the Extension Service of the University of Michigan for twenty-nine years before his retirement in 1974. He began as the supervisor of the Saginaw area extension program in 1946. In 1952, he was named supervisor of state-wide and community projects in art, music, theater, and creative writing. In 1962, he was appointed assistant director of the Extension Service and in 1971, he became director of cultural activities. In addition to these responsibilities, from 1960 to 1974, Church was also a lecturer in art at the University of Michigan College of Architecture and Design.
A native of Detroit, Church studied art at the Wicker Art School, Cranbrook Academy of Wayne State University, and the University of Michigan. In his career, Church attained a reputation as art lecturer and critic. He was once described by Reader's Digest as "Michigan's Evangelist of Art" for his popular talks and lectures, for his nurturing of Michigan artists, and for his work with numerous cultural and art organizations.
The Michael Church collection has been arranged into the following series: Biographical/personal; Cultural Organizations and Programs; Michigan Artists; Programs of Art Exhibitions; Audio-Visual Material; Clippings; and Other activities and interests. Of special interests are the files of collected information about local Michigan art organizations and the binders containing biographical information about Michigan artists.
Subjects:
Art--Michigan.; Arts--Michigan--Societies, etc.; Depressions--1929--Michigan.; United States. National Youth Administration.; University of Michigan. Extension Service.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Youth--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Anthony, Edward.; Art.; Ann Arbor Art Fairs (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Barnes, Al, 1904-; Books.; Cemeteries--Michigan.; Church, Michael P. (Michael Paul), 1907-; Dodge, Cynthia.; Libraries--Michigan.; Lumber industry.; Monteith, John, 1788-1868.; Monuments and memorials.; Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.; Music--Michigan.; Politics and government--1929-1938.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Tombs and sepulchral monuments.; University of Michigan. Extension Service.; Willow Run Bomber Plant.
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Hickey, Edward J. (Edward John), b. 1893.; Catholic Church. Archdiocese of Detroit (Mich.)
Genre Terms:
Motion pictures.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Biographical/personal
  - Biographical information, newspaper articles, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Certificates, Letter of introduction from President Fleming (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1933-1975
    - 1933-1972, 43 folders (Box 1)
    - 1973-1975, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - undated (Box 2)
      (filed alphabetically by correspondent)
  - Letters containing reference to Church 1937-1965 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous writings, 3 folders (Box 2)
- Cultural Organizations and Programs
  - Michigan state organizations
    - American Art Week (in Michigan) 1959 (Box 2)
    - American Art Week 1963 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Academy of Science, Arts, and Letters (Box 2)
    - Michigan Association of the Professions (Box 2)
    - Michigan Council for the Arts (Box 2)
    - Michigan Council for the Arts grant request forms and budgets 1971-1973 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Council for the Arts Minutes 1972 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Education Association (Box 2)
    - Michigan League of Hand Weavers (Box 2)
    - Michigan Orchestra Association. (Box 2)
    - Michigan Pageants (Box 2)
    - Michigan Theaters (Box 2)
    - Michigan Water Color Society (Box 2)
    - Michigan Week 1962 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Writers (Box 2)
    - Monteith (John) birthplace, includes biographical material (Box 2)
  - Michigan local community organizations
    - Alma Arts & Crafts Center (Box 2)
    - Alpena (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor, (Active) (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor, Conference on Natural beauty (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor, Area Goals Committee (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor, Art Association (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor, Civic Art Committee (formerly, Committee on Art & Design), 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor, Ann Arbor Group (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor, People to People (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor, Potter's Guild (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor, UM-2nd Amateur Art Exhibition 1956; criticism, Suomi College Art Exhibition, 1956; Oil Painting Exhibit (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor, Ann Arbor Street Art Fair, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor Summer Art Conference 1960-1973
      - 1960 (Box 3)
      - 1962 (Box 3)
      - 1963 (Box 3)
      - 1964 (Box 3)
      - 1965 (Box 3)
      - 1966 (Box 3)
      - 1968 (Box 3)
      - 1969 (Box 3)
      - 1970 (Box 3)
      - 1971 (Michigan Invitational Exhibition) (Box 3)
      - 1972 (Box 3)
      - 1973 (Box 3)
    - Battle Creek, and Kellogg C.C. (Box 3)
    - Battle Creek, Battle Creek Community United Arts Council (Box 3)
    - Battle Creek, Kellogg Foundation (Box 3)
    - Bay City (Box 3)
    - Benton Harbor (Box 3)
    - Berrien Springs (Box 3)
    - Birmingham (Box 3)
    - Birmingham, Boicourt (Box 3)
    - Birmingham Gallery (Box 3)
    - Birmingham, Little Gallery (Box 3)
    - Bloomfield Hills (Box 3)
    - Brighton (Box 3)
    - Bronson (Box 3)
    - Cadillac (Box 3)
    - Centreville, Glen Oaks Community College (Box 3)
    - Charlevoix (Box 3)
    - Cheboygan (Box 3)
    - Clawson, "Tints and Tones Art Association" (Box 3)
    - Coldwater, Tibbets Theater (Box 3)
    - Coopersville, Cultural Association (Box 3)
    - Dearborn (Box 3)
    - Dearborn, Ford Motor Company (Box 3)
    - Detroit, Correspondence, clippings 1959-1968 (Box 3)
    - Detroit, 1969-current, correspondence with George Pierrot (Box 3)
    - Detroit, Central Business District Association (Box 3)
    - Detroit, Galleries (Box 3)
    - Detroit, Fine Arts Committee of the Detroit Olympic Committee, Report 1963 (Box 3)
    - Detroit, The Palette Guild (Box 3)
    - Detroit, Parke-Davis (Box 3)
    - Detroit, Reynolds Metals Company (Box 3)
    - Detroit, SCARAB Club (Box 3)
    - Detroit, Society of Arts and Crafts, Topic And Talk (Box 3)
    - Dowagiac (Box 3)
    - East Jordan (Box 3)
    - Escanaba (Box 3)
    - Farmington (Box 3)
    - Flint (Box 3)
    - Flint, Mott Foundation (Box 3)
    - Frankfort (Box 4)
    - Fremont (Box 4)
    - Gaylord (Box 4)
    - Gibraltar (Historical Society) (Box 4)
    - Glen Arbor (Box 4)
    - Grand Haven (Box 4)
    - Grand Rapids (Box 4)
    - Grand Rapids, Art Museum (Box 4)
    - Grand Valley, Artists (Box 4)
    - Greenville (Box 4)
    - Grosse Pointe (Box 4)
    - Harbor Springs (Box 4)
    - Harrisville (Box 4)
    - Hartland (Box 4)
    - Hastings (Box 4)
    - Holland (Box 4)
    - Houghton (Box 4)
    - Huntington Woods (Box 4)
    - Ionia (Box 4)
    - Iron Mountain (Box 4)
    - Ironwood (Box 4)
    - Jackson (Box 4)
    - Jones (Box 4)
    - Kalamazoo (Box 4)
    - Kalamazoo, Institute of the Arts (Box 4)
    - Lansing Art Guild (Box 4)
    - Lansing Community Art Gallery (Box 4)
    - Lansing, Michigan State University (Box 4)
    - Livonia (Box 4)
    - Manistee (Box 4)
    - Marquette (Box 4)
    - Marquette Craftsmen's Conference 1961; speech given by Charles H. Sawyer (Box 4)
    - Marshall (Box 4)
    - Mason (Box 4)
    - Melvindale (Box 4)
    - Menominee, Catherine Grassl (Box 4)
    - Midland (Box 4)
    - Milan (Box 4)
    - Mount Clemens (Box 4)
    - Mount Pleasant, Central Michigan University (Box 4)
    - Munising (Box 4)
    - Muskegon (Box 4)
    - Negaunee (Box 4)
    - Niles (Box 4)
    - Northern Michigan Arts & Crafts (Box 4)
    - Orchard Lake, Polish American Studies (Box 4)
    - Owosso (Box 4)
    - Pequaming (Box 4)
    - Petoskey (Box 4)
    - Plymouth (Box 4)
    - Pontiac (Box 4)
    - Port Austin, Whispering Oaks Studio (Box 4)
    - Port Huron, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Port Huron, Blue Water Art Club (Box 4)
    - Quincy (Box 5)
    - Rochester, Oakland University (Box 5)
    - Royal Oak (Box 5)
    - Saginaw (Box 5)
    - St. Clair Shores Art League of Macomb County (Box 5)
    - St. Clair Shores, Lakeside Palette Club (Box 5)
    - St. Clair Shores, Macomb Art Society (Box 5)
    - St. Ignace (Box 5)
    - St. Joseph (Box 5)
    - Sault Ste. Marie, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Southgate (Box 5)
    - South Haven (Box 5)
    - Sparta (Box 5)
    - Tawas (Box 5)
    - Traverse City (Box 5)
    - Trenton (Box 5)
    - Trenton (Box 5)
    - UM, Fairlane Festival (Box 5)
    - UM general (Box 5)
    - UM Extension Service, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - UM Extension Service, Grand Rapids (Box 5)
    - UM Japanese Art Series, Calvin L. French (Box 5)
    - UM Don Gooch (Box 5)
    - UM Gerome Kamrowski (Box 5)
    - UM Anna Smith (Art Faculty) (Box 5)
    - UM Bentley Historical Library (Box 5)
    - UM Alfred W. Storey (Box 5)
    - Upper Peninsula (Box 5)
    - Upper Peninsula Crafts Council (Box 5)
    - Wayne (Box 5)
    - Wakefield (Box 5)
    - Wyandotte (Box 5)
  - Various
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
    - Artrain (Box 5)
    - Massachusetts (Box 5)
    - New York, The Kosciuszko Foundation (Box 5)
    - Youngstown, Ohio, Butler Institute of Art (Box 5)
    - Washington D.C., Lund, Wendell (Box 5)
    - West Virginia (Box 5)
    - Wyoming (Box 5)
    - Wyoming, Rupert Conrad (others) (Box 5)
    - Canada (Box 5)
    - Canada Arts Festival (Box 5)
    - Canada Willistead Art Gallery (Box 5)
- Michigan Artists
  - Biographical information about Michigan artists [A-H], 3 volumes (Box 6)
  - Notebooks containing biographical information about Michigan artists [I-S], 3 volumes (Box 7)
    (The T-Z notebooks were never received)
  - Various biographical information (to be processed) (Box 7)
- Programs of Art Exhibitions
  - Various, 25 folders (Box 8)
  - Summer Conference 1970 (Box 8)
  - Gallery Invitational 1970 (Box 8)
- Audio-Visual Material
  - Sound recordings
    - Various (Box 8)
      (include interview with Edward Hickey, July 1968; and recordings from art conference programs)
  - Photographs
    - Portraits; Michael Paul Church (MPC) at cultural meetings, etc. (Box 8)
    - Franklin Delano Roosevelt visit to Grand Rapids 1936 (Box 8)
    - Lumbering; Chief Thundercloud (Box 8)
    - Slides 1972 of Ann Arbor Street Art Fair (Box 8)
    - John Monteith Gettysburg cemetery dedication 1960s; include portraits of John Monteith (Box 8)
  - Film Strip
    - "Material Handling Aids Victory" produced by Ford Motor Willow Run Bomber Plant 1944 (Box 8)
  - Film
    - "Images of Michigan" 1959 "Michigan Week" series produced by MPC for WWJ-TV, Detroit., 1000 feet; sound; b&w, 16 mm (Box 9)
      (Include interviews of MPC with Al Barnes, Cynthia Dodge, and Edward Anthony)
    - "Images of Michigan" (copy), 1 videotapes U-matic; 3/4 inches; 16 mm (Box 9)
      (Copy made November 7, 1978)
- Clippings
  - Accounts of exhibitions, etc., 15 folders (Box 9)
  - Village Club Art Group (Dearborn, Michigan) scrapbook 1941-1963 (Box 9)
    (includes photographs)
- Other activities and interests
  - Youth activities 1930s
    - Paper concerning Michigan Youth during the depression circa 1939 (Box 10)
    - Pamphlets on the 1936 Presidential campaign (Box 10)
    - Frank Murphy clippings, speeches, and press statements (Box 10)
    - Good Neighbor League (Box 10)
    - American Youth Commission (Box 10)
    - American Youth Congress (Box 10)
    - National Youth Administration (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous, 3 folders (Box 10)
    - Youth Organizations (various information on) (Box 10)
    - Directory of Community Service Programs of Michigan. W.P.A. (Box 10)
    - Young Democrats (Box 10)
    - Young Democrats, State Central Committee (District Chairman) (Box 10)
    - Michigan Youth Survey Project (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous papers on employment and leisure for youth 1930s (Box 10)
    - Boys vocational school, Lansing, Includes report by church (Box 10)
    - "Your youth reporter", letters from Europe 1939 by Orin Kaye. (Box 10)
  - Extension Service (University of Michigan)
    - Annual Report, 1948-1965
      - July 1, 1948-June 30, 1949 (Box 10)
      - July 1, 1950-June 30, 1951 (Box 10)
      - July 1, 1952-June 30, 1953 (Box 10)
      - 1955-1956 (Box 10)
      - 1956-1957 (Box 10)
      - 1957-1958 (Box 10)
      - 1958-1959 (Box 10)
      - July 1, 1959-June 30, 1960 (Box 10)
      - 1960-1961 (Box 10)
      - 1961-1962 (Box 10)
      - 1965 (Box 10)
    - University of Michigan Extension Service, Special Projects Division, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - University of Michigan Extension Service, Saginaw Valley (Box 10)
    - University of Michigan Extension Service, Flint (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Veterans' Affairs and the Public Information Program (Box 10)
    - Oral History Project, with some correspondence between the MHC and donors 1955-1957 (Box 10)
    - University of Michigan, Civil Defense Committee (Box 10)
    - Board for Fundamental Education, Exchange program w. Brit. Honduras and Belize, Ann Arbor's "sister city" (Box 10)
    - Correspondence related to a painting of the University Observatory executed by Prof. Aarre Lahti (Box 10)